# Francisco Costela, PhD

Harvard Medical School, Boston, MA

☐ francisco.costela@gmail.com ☐+1 602 748

9461

Data Scientist

fcostela

in francisco-costela

# **Professional summary**

Extensive experience on data science, machine learning, computer vision, visual psychophysics, and eye tracking while working in vision science for 10+ years. I have developed a strong passion to work with big datasets, build predictive models, find trends, and produce stunning reports. I want to keep applying my knowledge within technologies involving machine learning and computer vision. 4+ years professional programming. Technical literacy and project management. Open to relocate.

### Relevant skills

AI/ML Python/TensorFlow, Keras, Scikit-learn, Numpy, Pandas, NLP

Coding Adept at Python and Matlab. Knowledge of C/C++, Java, Stata

Databases SQL, Excel - Web development mySQL, HTML, CSS, PHP

Visualization OpenCV, Plotly, Seaborn, Illustrator, Powerpoint, Psychtoolbox, Tableau

Research 20 peer reviewed articles Google Scholar- 27 verified reviews Publons link

Communication 21 contributions to international meetings, including ICMLT, ARVO, SFN, VSS

## **Employment**

2019-present

ML innovator, as Research Programmer at Harvard Medical School, Boston, MA.

- Implemented feed-forward neural networks to predict hazard detection in driving videos using features from eye tracking data
- Conducted NLP analyses to evaluate cognitive and visual function. Gathered crowd-sourcing responses from auditory descriptions using Amazon Mechanical Turk
- Developed recurrent neural (LSTM) networks and Taylor series methods to boost prediction of gaze landing on gaze-contingent paradigms
- Created a new Quality of Life instrument to evaluate functional vision from a population of 500 patients with retinitis pigmentosa (RP) using Rasch analysis

2015-present

Data scientist, as Sr Fellow at Schepens Eye Research Institute, Boston, MA.

- Built a freely open-access eye-movement database watching movies. Link
- $\circ$  Created clusters and archetypes (unsupervised learning) to classify visual functional fields and correlate with hereditary patterns in a population with RP
- Applied gaze tracking and video processing to identify the preferred retinal locus used by people with low vision while watching video
- Developed visual rehabilitation techniques based on zoom/bubble magnification and dynamic content guide for people with macular degeneration and hemianopia

2011-2014

Computer vision, as Researcher at Barrow Neurological Institute, Phoenix, AZ.

- Applied electrophysiology with macaques to map eye movements in the visual cortex
- Developed software and interface to import, process, and plot eye tracking data
- Wrote a thesis on the roles of fixational eye movements in perception, cognition, and oculomotor control developing psychophysics experiments

- 2009-2010 Medical imaging, as Researcher at Pablo de Olavide University, Seville, Spain.
  - Analysed fiber tract and DTI (Diffusion tensor imaging) from patients with dementia
  - Processed magnetic resonance image data using Freesurfer pipelines and FSL segmentation tools
  - 2009 Medical imaging, as Trainee at FMRI Oxford University, Oxford, UK.
    - Detected the stria of Gennari (area in the visual cortex) in brain MRI scans
- 2007–2008 **Senior Programmer**, *Ebrisa*, Chicago, USA, MyEclipse, J2EE, Struts, Hibernate, MySQL, Css, Taglibs, XML.
- 2006–2007 **Junior Programmer**, Telefonica I+D, Madrid, Spain, JAVA Technology, J2EE, JABX, SOAP, XML, Javascript, Beanshells, PJTools, Oracle Database.
- 2005–2006 **Junior Programmer**, *Ocean Lab*, Edinburgh, UK, Design of an autonomous underwater vehicle. Sonar management, C++, OpenCV **₹**Link.
  - 2005 **Trainee**, *MADOC*, Granada, Spain, Maintenance and development of applications involving database access to Oracle and Access from Delphi and Jbuilder.

## **Education**

- 2011-2014 PhD in Neuroscience, Arizona State university, Tempe, AZ, USA.
- 2019-2010 MSc in Neuroscience, Pablo de Olavide University, Seville, Spain.
- 2008-2009 MSc in Biomedical Engineering, Oxford University, Oxford, UK.
- 2005-2006 BSc Computer Engineering thesis, Heriot-Watt University, Edinburgh, UK.
- 2000-2005 BSc Computer Engineering, University of Granada, Granada, Spain.

## Other work experience

- 2017-present "Vision: A System and its Assessment Eye Movements", Lecturer, Harvard University/Schepens Eye Research Institute, 2 semesters.
- 2016-present "IMFAHE Fellowship", Advisor, Spain-USA, 10 grad students.
- 2015-present "International Mentor Program", Mentor, Spain-USA, 4 grad students.
  - 2013-2014 "BIO 201 Anatomy and Physiology", Graduate Teaching Associate, School of Life Sciences, Arizona State University, 3 semesters.
  - 2011-2012 "Ask a biologist", GPSA Volunteer, Arizona State University.
  - 2009-2010 "Spanish", Spanish Official Helper, Oxford Language Centre.

#### Courses

- 2018 Successful grant writing, Harvard Catalyst.
- 2017 Effectively communicating research, Harvard Catalyst.
- 2015-2016 Certificate in Applied Biostatistics, Harvard Catalyst.
  - 2015 Fundamentals of Clinical and Translational Research, Harvard Catalyst.
  - 2013 Machine Learning, Coursera Stanford University.
  - 2009 MRI Physics course, FMRIB Oxford.